Guide to the Estela and Ernesto Bravo Film and Video Collection TAM.616
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series VIII: Fidel: The Untold Story and Anecdotes about Fidel, 1995-2002
  - Fusté, Tomás García: Interview (part 2), circa 1995-2000; cuid17988 (Box 97, Dvd ref1000)
    This video features an interview with Miami radio host Tomás García Fusté. The video begins with footage of images in Fusté's office and an interview that starts at minute 5:30. Fusté begins by speculating about end of the Castro presidency, which he predicts will occur within a year of the time in which the interview was conducted. He also talks about his family members still living in Cuba, and the state of the country. He discusses Cuban exiles who have attempted to reach the US by raft or in the Mariel Boatlift, and blames Castro for the tragedies that had have happened as a result of people fleeing the country. Finally, Fusté discusses other anti-Castro Cubans in the United States including Orlando Bosch and Jorge Mas Canosa.
  - Gades, Antonio: Interview, 1996 August 7; cuid17989 (Box 69, Cassette ref888, Box 85, Dvd ref888)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:21:44.
  - Garcia, Juanita Vera: Interview, circa 1995-2000; cuid319 (Box Digitized Access Files, File tam616_ref213)
    Juanita Vera Garcia was Fidel Castro's official translator. She has also worked as the official translator for Raul Castro.
    Juanita Vera Garcia reflects on her impressions of Fidel Castro, including his outlook, ideology, and appearance. She discusses the impact of Cuba's military intervention in Angola on Castro and his legacy.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:14:32.
  - Garcia, Juanita Vera: Interview 2, Tape B, circa 1995-2000; cuid320 (Box Digitized Access Files, File tam616_ref219)
    Juanita Vera Garcia describes her experiences working as a translator for Fidel Castro. She talks about her translation work, Castro's work habits, his long public speeches, his personality and its effect on the people around him, and the people she has met while working as Castro's interpreter.
  - Gonzalez, Elián (and his lawyer), 2000; cuid17990 (Box 69, Cassette ref876, Box 84, Box ref876)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:31:50.
  - González, Elián CNN footage, circa 2000; cuid17991 (Box 62, Cassette ref1034, Box Digitized Access Files, Cassette tam616_ref1034)
  - González, Elián- "extracts from VHS", circa 2000; cuid17992 (Box 97, Dvd ref226)
    This video features footage of Elián González in Cuba. The video begins with extended footage of González arriving in Cuba with his father. As he and his father depart from the plane they are greeted by large crowds and a group of relatives including González's grandparents. The video then cuts to footage of crowds lining the street as González rides home. The video also features footage of Elián González at the beach with his family, going to school, and ends with footage of him reading La Edad de Oro by José Martí, which was a gift from Fidel Castro.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:23:32.
  - González, Elián "Comp Reel", circa 2000; cuid17993
    Duration: 90 minutes
  - González (Quintana), Juan Miguel: Interview, 2000 November; cuid17994 (Box 68, Cassette ref844, Box 83, Dvd ref844)
    Juan Miguel González Quintana is the father of Elián González.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:31:35.
  - González (Quintana), Juan Miguel: Interview, continuation, 2000 November; cuid17995 (Box 68, Cassette ref845, Box 83, Dvd ref845)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:22:40.
  - González (Quintana), Juan Miguel: Interview 1, 2000; cuid17996 (Box 62, Cassette ref1053)
  - González (Quintana), Juan Miguel: Interview 2, 2000; cuid17997 (Box 62, Cassette ref1055)
  - González (Quintana), Juan Miguel: Interview 3, 2000; cuid17998 (Box 62, Cassette ref1054)
  - González (Quintana), Juan Miguel: Interview, 2000; cuid17999
  - González Corrales, Manuel: Interview, circa 1995-2000; cuid18000 (Box 97, Dvd ref80)
    Manuel González Corrales (1916-2014) was a friend of Fidel Castro at the University of Havana.
    This video begins with a brief discussion with one of Fidel Castro's university classmates about a 1980 reunion between Castro and his friends from the University of Havana. The brief footage focuses on a photograph from the event. At minute 3:35 the video changes to an interview with Manuel González Corrales. He discusses his memories of Fidel Castro at the University of Havana and their shared involvement in student activism. He describes the political environment within the university as a microcosm and training ground for the revolutionary movements that developed in Cuba, and later discusses the assassination of Student Federation leader Manolo Castro.
  - "González, Manuel Corrales Cassette #47", circa 1995-2000; cuid18001 (Box 46, Cassette ref996)
  - Guevara, Alfredo: Interview (part 1), 1996 May 27; cuid18002 (Box 70, Cassette ref907, Box 85, Dvd ref907)
    Alfredo Guevara Valdes (1925-2013) was a lifelong friend of Fidel Castro. They were students at the University of Havana, where Guevara was a member of the Communist Youth organization. After the Cuban revolution, Guevara became vice minister of Culture and established the Cuban Institute for Arts and Cinematography (I.C.A.I.C.), which sponsored Cuba's state-funded cinema. After leaving the ICAIC 1982, he spent nine years as Cuban ambassador to the United Nations educational, scientific and cultural organization (UNESCO).
  - Guevara, Alfredo: Interview (part 2), 1996 May 27; cuid18003 (Box 86, Dvd ref997)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:26:22.
  - Guevara, Aleida: Interview (part 1), 1996; cuid322 (Box 63, Cassette ref1064, Box 96, Dvd ref1064)
    Aleida Guevara March (1960- ) is the eldest daughter of four children born to Ernesto "Che" Guevara and his second wife, Aleida March. A medical doctor, Guevara is based at the William Soler Children's Hospital in Havana and has also worked as a physician in Angola, Ecuador, and Nicaragua.
    In this interview Aleida Guevara begins with a discussion about her earliest memories of Fidel Castro. She then discusses Castro asking her to write a prolog for a book about her father, Ernesto "Che" Guevara, and his role supporting the unsuccessful revolution in Congo. She describes her enjoyment writing the prolog because it allowed her to revisit positive memories of her father. She also describes Castro's relationship with Guevara, and how Castro convinced him to return to Cuba briefly before he left to support guerilla forces in Bolivia. In the last half of the interview, she reads from the letter Castro wrote to her father convincing him to return to Cuba.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:23:28.
  - Guevara, Aleida: Interview (part 1), 1998 June 21; cuid324 (Box 95, Dvd ref1396)
  - Guevara, Aleida: Interview (part 2), 1998 June 21; cuid325 (Box 95, Dvd ref71)
  - Guevara, Aleida: Interview (part 3), 1998 June 21; cuid326 (Box 86, Dvd ref64)
  - Guevara, Aleida: Interview (part 4), 1998 June 21; cuid327 (Box 95, Dvd ref67)
  - Haines, Randa: Interview, 1996 November 9; cuid18004 (Box 68, Cassette ref873, Box 84, Dvd ref873)
    Randa Haines (1945- ) is a film and television director and producer, most famous for directing the film Children of a Lesser God.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:16:50.
  - Heath, Edward: Interview, 1996 March 15; cuid328 (Box 76, Dvd ref51)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:24:23.
  - Hernández, Melba: Interview, circa 1995-2000; cuid18005 (Box 69, Cassette ref905, Box 85, Dvd ref905)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:31:41.
  - Hernández, Melba: Interview, circa 1995-2000
    - Hernández, Melba: Interview, circa 1995-2000; cuid18006 (Box 76, Dvd ref73)
      Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:30:01.
    - Hernández, Melba: Interview, circa 1995-2000; cuid18007
  - Hernández, Melba: Interview, circa 1995-2000
    - Hernández, Melba: Interview, circa 1995-2000; cuid18008 (Box 76, Dvd ref81)
      Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:26:55.
    - Hernández, Melba: Interview, circa 1995-2000; cuid18009
  - Hernández, Melba: Interview, circa 1995-2000
    - Hernández, Melba: Interview, circa 1995-2000; cuid18010 (Box 76, Dvd ref83)
      Original Format: Betacam. Recording is divided into 2 access DVDs. Duration: Part 1 - 00:16:31; Part 2 - 00:12:54.
    - Hernández, Melba: Interview, circa 1995-2000; cuid18011
  - Hernández, Melba: Interview, circa 1995-2000
    - Hernández, Melba: Interview, circa 1995-2000; cuid18012 (Box 76, Dvd ref89)
      Original Format: Betacam. Recording is divided into 4 access DVDs. Duration: Part 1 - 00:15:11; Part 2 - 00:01:50; Part 3 - 00:00:43; Part 4 - 00:11:41.
    - Hernández, Melba: Interview, circa 1995-2000; cuid18013
  - Hernández, Melba: Interview, circa 1995-2000
    - Hernández, Melba: Interview, circa 1995-2000; cuid18014 (Box 76, Dvd ref97)
      Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:29:26.
    - Hernández, Melba: Interview, circa 1995-2000; cuid18015
  - Hernández, Melba: Interview with Ana Fidelia, circa 1995-2000
    - Hernández, Melba: Interview with Ana Fidelia, circa 1995-2000; cuid18016 (Box 76, Dvd ref113)
      Original Format: Betacam. Recording is divided into 4 access DVDs. Duration: Part 1 - 00:05:26; Part 2 - 00:02:35; Part 3 - 00:01:20, Part 4 - 00:01:20.
    - Hernández, Melba: Interview with Ana Fidelia, circa 1995-2000; cuid18017
  - Interview List, undated; cuid18018 (Box 72, Folder 6)
  - Interview Transcripts, 1996; cuid18019 (Box 72, Folder 7-12)
  - Jackson, Jesse: Interview, 1996 September 17; cuid329 (Box 86, Dvd ref33)
  - Jiménez, Antonio Núñez: Interview (with stills), 1996
    - Jiménez, Antonio Núñez: Interview Recording (with stills), 1996; cuid18020 (Box 69, Cassette ref891, Box 85, Dvd ref891)
      Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:21:52.
    - Jiménez, Antonio Núñez: Interview Transcript, 1996; cuid18021
  - Jiménez, Antonio Núñez: Interview, 1996
    - Jiménez, Antonio Núñez: Interview Recording, 1996; cuid18022 (Box 76, Dvd ref50)
      Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:30:43.
    - Jiménez, Antonio Núñez: Interview Transcript, 1996; cuid18023
  - Jiménez, Antonio Núñez: Interview, 1996
    - Jiménez, Antonio Núñez: Interview Recording, 1996; cuid18024; 4 items 3 access CDs and 1 video cassette (Box 76, Dvd ref108)
      Original Format: Betacam. Recording is divided into 3 access DVDs. Duration: Part 1 - 00:08:50; Part 2 - 00:18:34; Part 3 - 00:03:45.
    - Jiménez, Antonio Núñez: Interview Transcript, 1996; cuid18025
  - Jiménez, Antonio Núñez: Interview, 1996
    - Jiménez, Antonio Núñez: Interview Recording, 1996; cuid18026; 4 items 3 access CDs and 1 video cassette (Box 76, Dvd ref109)
      Original Format: Betacam. Recording is divided into 3 access DVDs. Duration: Part 1 - 00:22:23; Part 2 - 00:01:32; Part 3 - 00:04:09.
    - Jiménez, Antonio Núñez: Interview Transcript, 1996; cuid18027
  - Jiménez, Antonio Núñez: Interview, 1996 May 29
    - Jiménez, Antonio Núñez: Interview Recording, 1996 May 29; cuid18028 (Box 70, Cassette ref908, Box 85, Dvd ref908)
      Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:06:09.
    - Jiménez, Antonio Núñez: Interview Transcript, 1996 May 29; cuid18029
  - Landau, Saul: Interview (part 1), circa 1995-2000; cuid330 (Box 62, Cassette ref1045)
  - Landau, Saul: Interview (part 2), circa 1995-2000; cuid331 (Box 62, Cassette ref1046)
  - Leal, Eusebio: Interview, circa 1995-2000; cuid332 (Box 96, Dvd ref110)
    Eusebio Leal was the historian for the city of Havana.
    This tape includes a partial interview with Cuban historian Eusebio Leal, and begins part way through the interview. Leal discusses the relationship between Fidel Castro and his brother Raúl, which he describes as one of extreme confidence and closeness. Leal also describes the relationship between Castro and other prominent individuals in Cuba including Che Guevara, Celia Sanchez, Carlos Rafael Rodríguez, Conchita Fernandez, and Baudillo Castellano. Finally, he discusses Castro as a polarizing figure and talks about the opposition of many Cubans to his leadership. The last two minutes of the video feature background footage of Leal walking through a courtyard.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:13:22.
  - Leal, Eusebio: Interview, circa 1995-2000; cuid333 (Box 95, Dvd ref111)
  - Lesnik, Max: Interview, 1996 October 2; cuid18030 (Box 69, Cassette ref882, Box 84, Dvd ref882)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:27:02.
  - Lesnik, Max: Interview, 1996 October 2; cuid334 (Box 86, Dvd ref55)
  - Lesnik, Max: Interview, 1996 October 2; cuid18031 (Box 97, Dvd ref63)
    Max Lesnik was a Cuban revolutionary who attended the University of Havana with Fidel Castro.
    This video features an interview with Max Lesnik. Lesnik begins by discussing student activism at the University of Havana and clashes with Fulgencio Batista's government. He later discusses Fidel Castro's relationship with his first wife Mirta Díaz-Balart. He later describes Fidel's interest weapons and military action, and describes how the beginnings of Castro's coalition grew out of a militant faction he developed within the Partido Ortodoxo (Orthodox Party). Lesnik details Castro's personality as a young man and suggests that peers viewed him as audacious and likely to achieve prominence. He later addresses a question about racism and notes that as a Jewish man he did face some racism in Cuba, but argues that the generation that he and Castro were a part of held much less prejudice.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:29:23.
  - Levinson, Sandra: Interview, circa 1996-2000; cuid18032 (Box 75, Dvd ref32)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:30:00.
  - Levinson, Sandra: Interview (continued), circa 1996-2000; cuid18033 (Box 75, Dvd ref30)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:26:33.
  - Linares, Omar: Interview, circa 1996-2000; cuid18034 (Box 9, Cassette ref51)
  - Llorente, Armando: Interview (part 1), circa 1996-2000; cuid335 (Box 95, Dvd ref990)
    This video features a segment of an interview with Father Armando Llorente. In the interview Llorente introduces himself, and begins by discussing how he and several other Jesuit priests traveled from Spain to Cuba in 1942 to teach in Cuban schools. He explains that he was placed in el Colegio de Belen, where he met Fidel Castro who was a student at the school. He discusses what Castro was like as a student and an athlete, and describes him as particularly diligent. He shares a long anecdote about Castro's interest in basketball, and also talks about Castro's interest in other sports including soccer, baseball, and track.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:15:39.
  - Llorente, Armando: Interview (part 2), circa 1996-2000; cuid336 (Box 63, Cassette ref1063, Box 96, Dvd ref1063)
    In this portion of an interview the Father Armando Llorente, Llorente shares anecdotes about Fidel Castro when he was a student at el Colegio Belen. He first shares a story about a time Castro saved him while they were trying to cross a flooding river during a school camping trip. He then talks about an incident when Castro was almost expelled because he refused reveal the location of two missing classmates to the school's rector. Llorente explains that the students had left school in the immediate aftermath of Pearl Harbor to volunteer to fight in World War II, and Castro had promised to keep their decision secret. Finally, he looks through a yearbook from Colegio Belen, and points out a description about Castro in the yearbook.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:13:20.
  - Llorente, Armando: Interview (also Ed Murrow), circa 1995-2000; cuid337 (Box 86, Dvd ref57)
  - Llorente, Armando: Interview, circa 1995-2000; cuid338 (Box 86, Dvd ref58)
  - Llorente, Armando: Interview, circa 1995-2000; cuid339 (Box 86, Dvd ref62)
  - Lockwood, Lee: Interview, 1996 August 21; cuid18035 (Box 68, Cassette ref863, Box 84, Dvd ref863)
    During this interview, Lee Lockwood shows many of his Cuban photographs.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:27:23.
  - Lockwood, Lee: Interview, 1996 August 22; cuid340 (Box 95, Dvd ref984)
    Lee Lockwood is an American Journalist who documented Fidel Castro and Cuba in the decade following the Cuban revolution in his 1967 book "Castro's Cuba, Cuba's Fidel."
  - Lockwood, Lee: Interview (part 2), 1996 August 21; cuid341 (Box 96, Dvd ref1058)
    This video contains no audio. It features close-up shots of several of Lee Lockwood's photographs of Fidel Castro. Photos largely feature a young Castro at his home, playing sports, giving speeches, and smoking cigars.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:04:17.
  - Lockwood, Lee, 1996 August 21; cuid342 (Box 86, Dvd ref21)
  - Mandela, Nelson, with Jorge Risquet and Juan Almeida, circa 1995-2000; cuid18036
    Juan Almeida and Jorge Risquet meet with Nelson Mandela, exchanging words of greetings and thanks.
  - Márquez, Gabriel García: Interview, 1996 July 12; cuid18037 (Box 69, Cassette ref901, Box 85, Dvd ref901)
  - Márquez, Gabriel García: Interview, 1996 July 12; cuid18038 (Box 69, Cassette ref902, Box 85, Dvd ref902)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:21:36.
  - McGovern, George: Interview, 1996 August 31; cuid18039 (Box 75, Dvd ref22)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:12:23.
  - McGovern, George: Interview and Wayne Smith Interview, 1996 August 30
    - McGovern, George: Interview and Wayne Smith Interview Recording, 1996 August 30; cuid18040 (Box 68, Cassette ref865, Box 84, Dvd ref865)
      The footage begins with a 14-minute interview with Wayne Smith followed by almost four minutes of still photos, first of Fidel Castro and Smith, then followed by what appear to be photos in George McGovern's office, including photos of McGovern with Bill Clinton and with Castro. At around 18 minutes, the interview with McGovern begins.
      George McGovern speaks in the interview about his first speech in the Senate (1963) on the subject of US-Cuba relations and his continued support for normalization. He talks about his initial meeting with Fidel in 1975, which lasted fourteen hours over the course two days. He later discusses the powerful influence the Miami Cuban community holds in respect to American foreign policy toward Cuba.
      Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:28:25.
    - McGovern, George: Interview and Wayne Smith Interview Transcript, 1996 August 30; cuid18041
  - Menchu, Rigoberta: Interview, 1996 October 8; cuid18042 (Box 98, Dvd ref1061)
    This video features a brief interview with Guatemalan human rights activist Rigoberta Menchu. Menchu discusses the way people in the third world and Latin America view Fidel Castro, and explains that many see him as a symbol of resistance against imperialism. She discusses the cold or distant reception Castro has received from politicians in the United States over the years. She explains that although political and business leaders largely oppose his presidency, opinions about Castro, even in the United States, are very diverse.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:07:05.
  - Menchu, Rigoberta: Interview, 1996; cuid18043 (Box 1, Betacam ref255)
  - Menoyo, Eloy Gutierrez: Interview, circa 1995-2000; cuid343 (Box 86, Dvd ref60)
  - Menoyo, Eloy Gutierrez: Interview, circa 1995-2000; cuid344 (Box 86, Dvd ref61)
  - Mina, Gianni: Interview (part 1), circa 1995-2000; cuid345 (Box 95, Dvd ref105)
    Gianni Mina is an Italian journalist, writer and tv host who interviewed Fidel Castro in 1987. Excerpts of his interview with Castro were published in his book Human Rights in Cuba.
    This video contains an interview with Italian journalist Gianni Mina. Mina begins by discussing his background and personal history. He describes his early interest in sports journalism, and later becoming interested in politics after meeting exiled Brazilian youth living in Italy. He describes traveling to Brazil with friends and meeting Latin American intellectuals including Gabriel García Márquez. He later discusses an attempt to interview Fidel Castro at a boxing match in Monaco. He describes interviewing Castro 13 years after his initial attempt, and credits Márquez with facilitating the interview. He describes his interview with Castro in which they discussed Cuban human rights, scientific research, and the death of Che Guevara. The video contains frequent background noise, which makes some of the interview difficult to hear in places.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:20:49.
  - Mina, Gianni: Interview (part 2), circa 1995-2000; cuid18044 (Box 97, Dvd ref118)
    This interview with Gianni Mina begins with a discussion about Fidel Castro's relationship with Che Guevara. Mina explains that Castro only discussed his professional relationship with Guevara, and notes that Castro expressed his disagreement with Guevara's decisions to support revolutionary movements in the third world. In particular he noted that Castro thought Guevara was impatient in his efforts to support revolutionary movements in Bolivia. The second half of the interview focuses on Castro's meeting with Pope John Paul II. Mina discusses the reasons he thought the two men sought the meeting, and what each gained from the encounter. The video ends with a discussion about the role of the Catholic church in Latin America.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:31:07.
  - Mina, Gianni: Interview (part 3), circa 1995-2000; cuid18045 (Box 97, Dvd ref120)
    This final interview with Gianni Mina begins with a discussion about the meeting between Pope John Paul II and Fidel Castro. Mina explains the motivations of each for convening the meeting and the message it sent to Catholics in Latin America and world leaders. Mina also discusses his perceptions of Fidel Castro's personality and his public persona. Finally, he talks about Castro's friendship with novelist Gabriel García Márquez.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:26:36.
  - Mitterrand, Danielle: Interview, 1996 March 12; cuid18046 (Box 70, Cassette ref919, Box 85, Dvd ref919)
  - Mitterrand, Danielle: Interview, 1996 March 12; cuid18047 (Box 70, Cassette ref920, Box 85, Dvd ref920)
  - Moakley, Joseph: Interview, 1996 August 21; cuid18048 (Box Digitized Access Files, File tam616_ref25)
    The first 15 minutes of the video features shots of photographs and ephemera pertaining to Fidel Castro, including a magazine interview of Castro, Lee Lockwood's book/magazine cover, and a telegram from Castro to Lockwood. Parts of the video's first 15 minutes have no audio or video. The rest of the video contains out-of-sync footage from an interview with Representative Joseph Moakley. He discusses his first meeting with Castro, his visit to Cuba, and his views on the United States' foreign policy with Cuba, with particular emphasis on the US embargo of Cuba.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:29:08.
  - Moakley, Joseph: Interview, 1996 August 23; cuid18049 (Box 75, Dvd ref34)
  - Montane, Jesus: Interview, circa 1995-2000; cuid346 (Box 95, Dvd ref82)
    Jesus Montane Oropesa (1923-1999) was a Cuban revolutionary who participated in the Moncada assault on July 26, 1953, and remained a close friend and confidant of Fidel Castro.
  - Montane, Jesus: Interview, circa 1995-2000; cuid347 (Box 95, Dvd ref84)
  - Montane, Jesus: Interview, circa 1995-2000; cuid348 (Box 95, Dvd ref87)
  - Montiel, Magda: Interview, 1996 October 2; cuid18050 (Box 69, Cassette ref881, Box 84, Dvd ref881)
    Magda Montiel Davis (1953- ) is a Cuban American immigration lawyer who has pushed to improve relations between the United States and Cuba.
  - Monteil, Magda: Interview, 1996; cuid349 (Box 86, Dvd ref65)
  - Ordóñez, Cosme: Interview, circa 1995-2000; cuid350 (Box 96, Dvd ref98)